Okay, so in this video then, we are going
to discuss another quality management tool
and technique called the cause and effect
diagram.
Now the cause and effect diagram is used
to get to the root cause of an issue.
Now in reality, there's many, many tools
that you might use to get to the root
cause of an issue, but
for the purpose of the
PMP exam, this is the
one that they ask about.
So if you ever get a question that says,
you know, they give you a scenario and
say, which tool should he use to get to
the underlying cause of the problem or the
root cause of this issue,
then this is the diagram
that you'd use, or this is
a tool that you would use.
And the tool is called cause and effect
diagram.
It's also called a fishbone diagram.
It's also known as an Ishikawa diagram,
right, from the person that developed it,
right, Ishikawa, he came up with this
diagram.
That's why it's known as Ishikawa diagram.
It can also be known as a Y-Y-Y diagram,
right?
Because it's Basically, you're asking a
certain number of why.
You're asking continuous questions to
eventually get to the
root cause of the problem.
So make sure you know these terms,
cause and effect, fishbone, Ishikawa,
or even Y, Y, Y.
So make sure you know all of those terms,
you could see any of
these terms on the exam.
Now, you just need to
know the very, very high
level basics of how to interpret that one.
Every industry uses this Issue Carver
diagram in their own way.
But the basic principle is, you have an
issue.
So this is the major issue.
Then you list out all possible causes of
the issue.
In this case, man, machine, material,
environment, management, method.
These are all the possible causes.
And different industries will have
different possible causes.
And then for each possible cause,
you drill down and ask, now initially when
this was developed, right, they used to
talk about the five Ys, right?
So you ask the five Ys.
You drill down five times, and that should
either get you to the root cause or that
should get you to a major decision point,
at least.
Now, it doesn't have to be the five Ys,
right?
I mean, the modern view is it doesn't have
to be the five Ys.
That's why it's also known as a Y-Y
diagram.
So basically, you are drilling down,
asking a certain number of questions,
why did that happen?
Why did that happen?
You're drilling down a certain number of
steps to get to the root cause,
or at least to a major decision point.
And that's really about as
much as what you need for
the P&P exam regarding
the cause and effect diagram.
So it's to get to the root cause.
It's called cause and effect, fishbone,
Ishikawa, or the Y, Y.
Right, you list out all possible causes.
you drill down and ask a certain number of
ys and that should either get you to the
root cause at least a major decision
point.